Learning-SICP学习小组
倾情制作
翻译&&时间轴
杨启钊
（windfarer）
压制&&特效
邓雄飞
（Dysprosium）
校对
邓雄飞
特别感谢
裘宗燕教授
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
编译
PROFESSOR: Last time, we took a look at
教授: 上节课 我们学习了
an explicit control evaluator for Lisp
一个显式控制的Lisp求值器
and that bridged the gap between all these high-level languages
它弥合了像Lisp
like Lisp and query language all that stuff
或者查询语言之类的高级语言
bridged the gap between that and a conventional register machine.
与传统寄存器机器之间的鸿沟
And in fact, you can think of the explicit control evaluator
事实上 你可以将显式控制求值器
either as, say the code for a Lisp interpreter
看作是 在一台常见的
if you wanted to implement it in the
寄存机器上实现的
assembly language of some conventional register transfer machine,
Lisp求值器的汇编代码
or, if you like, you can think of it as the microcode
或者 你可以把它看做是
of some machine that's going to be specially designed to run Lisp.
某台专门运行Lisp的机器的微程序
In either case,
无论是那种情况
Nwhat we're doing is we're taking a machine
我们都是把一台
that speaks some low-level language
处理低级语言的机器
and we're raising the machine
抬高到一个层次
to a high-level language like Lisp
以便处理像Lisp这样的高级语言
by writing an interpreter.
这是通过编写解释器来实现的
So for instance
来看个例子
here, conceptually,
这里 从概念上来说
here conceptually is a
从概念上来说 这是一台
a special purpose machine for computing factorials.
专用于计算阶乘的机器
It takes in five and puts out 120.
输入5 输出120
And what this special purpose machine is
这个专用机器实际上
actually a Lisp interpreter
是一个Lisp解释器
that's configured itself to run factorials
它将自己配置为计算阶乘
because you feed into it a description of the factorial machine.
因为你向它送入了一台阶乘机器的描述
So that's what an interpreter is.
这就是解释器
It configures itself to
它将自己配置为
emulate a machine whose description you read in.
模拟你所输入描述的机器
Now, inside the Lisp interpreter, what's that?
那么 在Lisp解释器里是什么?
Well, that might be your general register language interpreter
里面可能是通用的寄存器语言解释器
that configures itself to behave like a Lisp interpreter
它将自己配置成像Lisp解释器那样
because you put in a whole bunch of instructions
因为你输入了一系列用寄存器语言
in register language.
编写的指令
This is the explicit control evaluator.
这就是显式控制求值器
And then it also has some sort of library
它里面也有一些库
a library of primitive operators and Lisp operations
由基本运算符和Lisp运算
all sorts of things like that.
等等要素组成
That's the general strategy of interpretation.
这是解释执行的一般策略
And the point is, what we're doing
事实上 我们所做的是
is we're writing an interpreter
通过编写解释器
to raise the machine
将机器抬升到
to the level of the programs that we want to write.
我们程序所在的层次
Well, there's another strategy
当然 还有另外一种策略
a different one, which is compilation.
这种不同的策略就是编译
Compilation's a little bit different.
编译有一些不同
Here--
这里
here we might have produced
我们可能已经实现了
a special purpose machine for,
一个特定用途的机器
for computing factorials
用来计算阶乘
starting with some sort of machine that speaks register language
从某种使用寄存器语言的机器开始
except we're going to do a different strategy.
但是 我们将让它执行不同的策略
We take our factorial program.
把我们的阶乘程序
We use that as the source code into a compiler.
作为源代码输入编译器
What the compiler will do
编译器就会
is translate that factorial program
把这个阶乘程序
into some register machine language.
翻译成某种寄存器机器语言
And this will now be not the explicit control evaluator for Lisp
现在它并不是Lisp的显式控制求值器
this will be some register language for computing factorials.
而是某种用来计算阶乘的寄存器语言
So this is the translation of that.
这就是翻译的过程
That will go into some sort of loader
它将进入某种加载器
which will combine this code
它会把这些代码
with code selected from the library
和从程序库中选取的代码
to do things like primitive multiplication.
比如乘法运算等 结合在一起
And then we'll produce a load module
随后我们将生成一个加载模块
which configures the register language machine
它把寄存器语言机器配置成
to be a special purpose factorial machine.
一个专门用来计算阶乘的机器
So that's a, that's a different strategy.
这就是不同的策略
In interpretation,
在解释中
we're raising
我们把机器
the machine to the level of our language, like Lisp.
抬升到Lisp语言的层次
In compilation
而在编译中
we're taking our program and lowering
我们将我们的程序下降到
it to the language that's spoken by the machine.
机器语言的层次
Well, how do these two strategies compare?
那么 这两个策略有什么区别呢?
The compiler can produce code that will execute more efficiently.
编译器可以生成执行起来更有效率的代码
The essential reason for that
主要原因是
is that if you think about the register operations that are running
如果你考虑运行中的寄存器操作
the interpreter has to produce register operations
解释器需要生成寄存器的操作
which, in principle, are going to be general enough
从原则上来讲 它需要足够通用
to execute any Lisp procedure.
以支持任何Lisp过程的执行
Whereas the compiler only has to worry about
而编译器只需要
producing a special bunch of register operations for
生成一组特定的寄存器操作
for doing the particular Lisp procedure that you've compiled.
用来执行你所编译的那部分特定的Lisp过程
Or another way to say that
换一种说法
is that the interpreter is a general purpose simulator
解释器是一种通用的模拟器
that when you read in a Lisp procedure
当你输入一个Lisp过程时
then those can simulate the program described by that, by that procedure.
它们就会模拟那个过程所描述的程序
So the interpreter is worrying about making a general purpose simulator
所以解释器旨在成为一个通用模拟器
whereas the compiler, in effect,
而编译器 实际上
is configuring the thing to be the machine
只需要将东西配置成
that the interpreter would have been simulating.
解释器将要去模拟的机器
So the compiler can be faster.
所以编译器可以运行得更快
OK, On the other hand
另一方面
the interpreter is a nicer environment for debugging.
解释器更适合用来排查错误
And the reason for that is that we've got the
这是因为
the source code actually there.
我们的源代码实际上就在那里
We're interpreting it That's what we're working with.
我们正在解释它们
And we also have the library around.
并且库也在其中
See, the interpreter--the library sitting there is part of the interpreter.
看 库是解释器的一部分
The compiler only pulls out from the library
而编译器只会拉取
what it needs to run the program.
运行程序所需要的代码
So if you're in the middle of debugging
所以 如果你在排查错误的途中
and you might like to write a little extra program
你想写一些额外的代码
to examine some run time data structure
来考察运行过程中的数据类型
or to produce some computation
或者做一些
that you didn't think of when you wrote the program
在写程序时没有想到的计算
the interpreter can do that perfectly well
解释器可以完美搞定这些
whereas the compiler can't.
而编译器不行
So there are sort of dual, dual advantages.
所以它们各有优点
The compiler will produce code that executes faster.
编译器将生成运行更快的代码
The interpreter is a better environment for debugging.
而解释器是一种更适合排错的环境
And most Lisp systems end up having both
大多数Lisp系统最终将二者都实现了
end up being configured so you have an interpreter
这样你就可以在开发阶段
that you use when you're developing your code.
可以使用解释器
Then you can speed it up by compiling.
随后通过编译加速代码的运行
And very often,
并且通常
you can arrange that compiled code
你能够让被编译的代码
and interpreted code can call each other.
和被解释的代码互相调用
We'll see how to do that, That's not hard.
我们将学习如何做到 其实不难
OK
好
In fact, the way we'll--
事实上
in the compiler we're going to make
在我们将要构建的编译器中
the way we'll arrange for compiled coding
我们实现编译的代码和解释的代码
and interpreted code to call to call each other
互相调用的方式是
is that we'll have the compiler use exactly
我们让编译器和解释器使用
the same register conventions as the interpreter.
使用完全一致的寄存器约定
Well, the idea of a compiler
编译器的理念
is very much like the idea of an interpreter or evaluator.
与解释器或求值器的理念很像
It's the same thing.
它们是相同的
See, the evaluator walks over the code
求值器遍历代码
and performs some register operations.
产生一些寄存器操作
That's what we did yesterday.
就是我们昨天做的事情
Well, the compiler essentially would like to walk over the code
而编译器会读取代码
and produce the register operations
生成一些进行求值时
that the evaluator would have done
求值器会进行的
were it evaluating the thing.
相关寄存器操作
And that gives us some model
这就给我们提供了一个模型
for how to implement a zeroth-order compiler
来实现一个零阶编译器
a very bad compiler but essentially a compiler.
一个很差劲但是能用的编译器
A model for doing that
这种模型就是
is you just take the evaluator,
你用求值器
you run it over the code
把代码跑一遍
but instead of executing the actual operations
但不去执行实际的操作
you just save them away.
只是把它们保存下来
And that's your compiled code.
那就是你编译后的代码
So let me give you an example of that.
让我举个例子
Suppose we're going to compile--
假设我们要编译
Suppose we want to compile the expression f of x.
编译(F X) 这个表达式
So let's assume that
我们假设
we've got f of x in the exp register
EXP寄存器中保存着(F X)
and something in the environment register.
而ENV寄存器又保存着其它东西
And now imagine starting up the evaluator.
想象我们启动了求值器
Well, it looks at the expression
它读取了表达式
and it sees that it's an application.
判断它是一个应用
And it branches to a place in the
它分支到求值器代码中的一个地方
in the evaluator code we saw called ev-application.
我们之前见过的叫EV-APPLICATION的地方
And then it begins.
然后继续处理
It stores away the operands and unev
恢复运算对象和UNEV
and then it's going to put the operator in exp,
然后之后它将运算符放在EXP寄存器中
and it's going to go recursively evaluate it.
递归地对它求值
That's the process that we walk through.
这就是我们经历的过程
And if you start looking at the code,
如果你看代码
you start seeing some register operations.
会看到一些寄存器操作
You see assign to unev the operands
你会看到将运算对象赋值给UNEV寄存器
assign to exp the operator,
把运算符赋值给EXP
save the environment, generate that, and so on.
保存环境、生成新环境 等等
Well, if we look on the overhead here
如果我们来看下这里的投影
we can see those operations starting to be produced.
我们会看到产生的这些操作
Here's sort of the first real operation
这是求值器实际要进行的
that the evaluator would have done.
第一个操作
It pulls the operands out of the exp register
它将运算对象从EXP寄存器里取出来
and assigns it to unev.
并将它赋值给UNEV
And then it assigns something to the expression register,
然后它给EXP寄存器赋了某个值
and it saves continue
然后保存CONTINUE
and it saves env.
保存ENV
And all I'm doing here is writing down the register assignments
我在这里就只是寄存器赋值
that the evaluator would have done in executing that code.
这就是求值器求值代码时进行的操作
And can zoom out a little bit.
我们缩小画面看看
Altogether, there are about 19 operations there.
总计有19个操作
And this is the--this will be the piece of code
这些代码
up until the point where
对应着
the evaluator branches off to apply-dispatch.
求值器跳转到APPLY-DISPATCH代码之前
And in fact, in this compiler
事实上 在这个编译器中
we're not going to worry about apply-dispatch at all.
我们不需要再关心APPLY-DISPATCH了
We're going to have everything
我们有所有东西
we're going to have both interpreted code and compiled code.
我们拥有解释后和编译后的所有代码
Always evaluate procedures,
通常求值过程
always apply procedures by going to apply-dispatch.
是由APPLY-DISPATCH处理的
That will easily allow interpreted code and
这将让被解释后代码与编译后代码
compiled code to call each other.
很容易互相调用
Well, in principle, that's all we need to do.
从原理上来说 这样做足矣
You just run the evaluator.
只需运行求值器
So the compiler's a lot like the evaluator.
因而编译器非常像求值器
You run it, except it stashes away these operations
你运行它 唯一不同是你把操作存下来
instead of actually executing them.
而不是实际执行它们
Well, that's not, that's not quite true. there's
这其实不完全正确
There's only one little lie in that.
这里面我们撒了个小谎
What you have to worry about is if you have a, a predicate.
你需要关心的是：如果有个谓词
If you have some kind of test you want to do
如果你要进行某种测试
obviously, at the point when you're compiling it
显然 在你编译时
you don't know which branch of these--
你不知道这些分支中
of a conditional like this you're going to do.
哪条分支会被执行
So you can't say which one the evaluator would have done.
所以你不能确定求值器将对哪个求值
So all you do there is very simple.
因此在这里就很简单
You compile both branches.
你把两个分支全编译了
So you compile a structure that looks like this.
因此你编译出一个这样的结构
That'll compile into something that says,
它们都会被编译成
the code, the code for P.
首先是P的代码
And it puts its results in, say, the val register.
它把结果存入VAL寄存器
So you walk the interpreter over the predicate
解释器对谓词求值
and make sure that the result would go into the val register.
并保证结果会放到VAL寄存器中
And then you compile an instruction that says
随后你编译一条指令
branch if, if val is true
如果VAL是TRUE
to a place we'll call label one.
就转到LABEL1这个地方
Then we, we will put the code for B
然后我们写下B的代码
to walk the interpreter--walk the interpreter over B.
让解释器对B进行求值
And then go to put in an instruction that says,
然后写一句指令
go to the next thing, whatever
用来跳转到下一条指令
whatever was supposed to happen after this thing was done.
就是它结束之后要去的地方
You put in that instruction.
你放入那个指令
And here you put label one.
这里你写下LABEL1
And here you put the code for A.
这里写A的代码
And you put go to next thing.
然后又是跳转到下一条指令
So that's how you treat a conditional.
这就是处理条件分支的办法
You generate a little block like that.
你生成一小段这样的代码
And other than that
除此之外
this zeroth-order compiler is the same as the evaluator.
这个零阶编译器与求值器一模一样
It's just stashing away the instructions instead of executing them.
它只是把指令存起来 而不执行它们
That seems pretty simple,
看起来很简单
but we've gained something by that.
但我们已经取得了某些收获
See, already that's going to be more efficient than the evaluator.
它会比求值器更有效率
Because, if you watch the evaluator run
因为 如果你观察求值器的运行
it's not only generating the register operations we wrote down
它并不只是进行寄存器操作
it's also doing things to decide which ones to generate.
它还会决定执行哪个
So the very first thing it does, say here
它做的第一件事就是
here for instance, is go do some tests
以它为例 就是进行某些测试
and decide that this is an application
确定它是一个应用
and then branch off to the place that,
然后就跳转到
that handles applications.
处理应用的地方去
In other words, what the evaluator's doing
换句话说 求值器做的事情是
is simultaneously analyzing the code to see what to do
分析代码需要进行的运算
and running these operations.
同时并执行它们
And when you-- if you run the evaluator a million times
当你运行求值器一百万次
that analysis phase happens a million times
这个分析过程就进行一百万次
whereas in the compiler, it's happened once
而在编译器中 它只会进行一次
and then you just have the register operations themselves.
之后就只有寄存器操作了
Ok, that's a, a zeroth-order compiler
这就是零阶编译器了
but it is a wretched, wretched compiler.
但它是个拙劣的编译器
It's really dumb.
它挺蠢的
Let's--let's go back and,
让我们回过头来
and look at this overhead.
看看这张投影
So look at look at some of the operations this thing is doing.
看看这个东西做的一些操作
We're supposedly
我们想看看
looking at the operations in interpreting f of x.
在解释(F  X)时的操作
Now, look here what it's doing.
这里就是它做了什么
For example, here
举个例子 这里
it assigns to exp the operator in fetch of exp.
它将(OPERATOR (FETCH EXP))赋值给EXP
But see, there's no reason to do that, because this is--
其实没必要这样做
the compiler knows
因为编译器知道
that the operator, fetch of exp,  is f right here.
(OPERATOR (FETCH EXP))的值就是F
So there's no reason why this instruction should say that.
因此这个指令没理由存在
It should say, we'll assign to exp, f.
应该改为：要把F赋值给EXP
Or in fact, you don't need exp at all.
或者实际上 你完全不需要EXP
There's no reason it should have exp at all.
没有理由需要EXP
What, what did exp get used for?
EXP是用来做什么的?
Well, if we come down here
我们看这里
we're going to assign to val
我们对VAL赋值
look up the stuff in exp in the environment.
在环境里的EXP里寻找东西
So what we really should do
因此 我们实际上是要
get rid of the exp register altogether
替换掉所有的EXP寄存器
and just change this instruction to say,
把这个指令修改为
assign to val
给VAL赋值
look up the variable value
在环境中查找
of the symbol f in the environment.
符号F的值
Similarly
类似地
back up here, we don't need unev at all
回到这里 我们也完全不需要UNEV
because we know
因为我们知道
what the operands of fetch of exp are for this piece of code.
因为我们知道 (FETCH EXP)取出的运算对象
It's the, it's the list x.
就是'(X)
So in some sense
从某种意义上来说
you don't want unev and exp at all.
你完全不需要UNEV和EXP
See, what they really are in some sense,
看看它们实际上是什么
those aren't registers of the actual machine that's supposed to run.
它们不是实际运行机器的寄存器
Those are registers
它们实际上是
that have to do with arranging the thing that can simulate that machine.
为了模拟该机器的而设置的寄存器
So they're always going to hold expressions
所以它们保存一些表达式
which from the compiler's point of view,
以编译器的视角看来
are just constants,
它们就是常量
so can be put right into the code.
因此可以直接把它们放到代码中
So you can forget about all the operations
你可以忘掉那些关于
worrying about exp and unev
EXP和UNEV的操作
and just use those constants.
只用那些常量
Similarly, again, if we go, go back and look here
与之相似 如果我们回顾这里
there are things like assign to continue eval-args.
有像(ASSIGN CONTINUE EVAL-ARGS)之类的语句
Now, that has nothing to do with anything.
现在 它和任何东西都没有关系
That was just the evaluator
它只是求值器
keeping track of where it should go next
维护了下一步需要去哪
to evaluate the arguments in some, in some application.
在某些应用中对参数进行求值
But of course, that's irrelevant to the compiler,
当然 这与编译器没关系
because you-- the analysis phase will have already done that.
因为这个分析过程已经被编译器做完了
So this is completely irrelevant.
所以编译后的代码完全不需要它
So a lot of these, these assignments
因此许多向CONTINUE寄存器
to continue have not to do
赋值的操作都是无用的
where the running machine is supposed to continue
运行着的机器留着它们
in keeping track of its state.
是为了跟踪它的状态
It has to, to do with where the evaluator analysis should continue
是为了知道求值器的下一步分析
and those are completely irrelevant.
而它们是完全无关的
So we can get rid of them.
因此我们可以去掉它们
Ok, well, if we, if we simply do that,
那么 如果我们简单地
make those kinds of optimizations
进行这类优化
get rid, get rid of worrying about exp and unev
不再考虑EXP和UNEV
and get rid of these irrelevant register assignments to continue
去掉这些无关的寄存器赋值
then we can take this literal code
我们就可以找到这些代码
these sort of 19 instructions that the evaluator would have done
也就是求值器会执行的这19条指令
and then replace them.
给替换掉
Let's look at the, at the slide.
请看幻灯片
Replace them by--we get rid of about half of them.
我们去掉了大概一半
And again, this is just sort of filtering
同样 这就是某种过滤
what the evaluator would have done by getting rid of the irrelevant stuff.
把无关的东西去掉
And you see, for instance
你们看 比如说
here the--where the evaluator said,
这里 求值器说
assign val, look up variable value, fetch of exp
(ASSIGN VAL (LOOKUP 'F (FETCH ENV)))
here we have put in the constant f.
这里 我们放入了一个常量F
Here we've put in the constant x.
这里又放了一个常量X
So there's a, there's a little better compiler.
因此 这个编译器又稍微好一点
It's still pretty dumb.
但它还是比较蠢
It's still doing a lot of dumb things.
它仍会做很多蠢事
Again, if we go look at the slide again
我们再看幻灯片
look at the very beginning here
看最开头的地方
we see a save the environment
我们调用(SAVE ENV)保存环境
assign something to the val register
然后给VAL寄存器赋某个值
and restore the environment.
然后恢复环境
Where'd that come from?
它是从哪来的
That came from the evaluator back here saying
它来自求值器的这个地方
oh, I'm in the middle of evaluating an application.
哦 我在正在对一个应用求值
So I'm going to recursively call eval dispatch.
因此我要递归调用EVAL-DISPATCH
So I'd better save the thing I'm going to need later,
我最好把接下来要用到的东西
which is the environment.
保存到环境中
This was the result of recursively calling eval dispatch.
这就是递归调用EVAL-DISPATCH的结果
It was evaluating the symbol f in that case.
刚才那个例子就是对符号F求值的结果
Then it came back from eval dispatch,
从EVAL-DISPATCH中返回
restored the environment.
将环境恢复
But in fact,
但是实际上
the actual thing it ended up doing in the evaluation
这个求值过程中 所进行的操作
is not going to hurt the environment at all.
完全不会影响环境
So there's no reason to be saving the environment
所以这里没必要先保存环境
and restoring the environment here.
再恢复环境
Similarly
与之类似
here I'm saving the argument list.
这里 我们保存了参数表
That's a piece of the argument evaluation loop,
那是一个求值参数的循环
saving the argument list
先保存参数表
and here you restore it.
然后在这里恢复
But the actual thing that you ended up doing
但事实上最后
didn't trash the argument list.
并没有变更参数表
So there was no reason to save it.
所以不需要保存它
So another way to say, another way to say that
换种方式来说
is that the,
怎么说呢
the evaluator has to be maximally pessimistic
求值器需要最大限度地保持悲观
because as far from its point of view
因为 从它的视角来看
it's just going off to evaluate something.
只知道接下来是要对某些东西进行求值
So it better save what it's going to need later.
所以最好把稍后要用的都存下来
But once you've done the analysis,
一旦你完成了分析
the compiler is in a position to say
从编译器的角度就会考虑
well, what actually did I need to save?
哪些是我真正需要存下来的?
And doesn't need to do any--
我们需要去 --
it doesn't need to be as careful as the evaluator
它不需要像求值器一样小心翼翼
because it knows what it actually needs
因为它知道 实际需要什么
Well, in any case, if we do that
无论如何 如果我们完成了优化
and eliminate all those redundant saves and restores
消除掉所有多余的保存和恢复
then we can get it down to this.
那么我们可以得到这样的结果
And you see there are actually only three
我们可以发现
only three instructions that we actually need
只有三条指令是必须的
down from the initial 11 or so
从刚才的11条指令优化成这样
or the initial 20 or so in the original one.
或是从原始的20条指令优化而来
And that's just saying,
这告诉我们
of those register operations
对于这些寄存器操作
which ones did we actually need?
哪些是必需的?
Let me just sort of summarize that in another way,
让我换个方式来总结一下
just to show you in a little better picture.
我先给你们看一张图
Here's a picture of starting--
这张图片
This is looking at all the saves and restores.
展示了所有的保存和恢复
So here's the expression, f of x
这里是表达式(F X)
and then this traces through, on the bottom here
在下面这里
the various places in the evaluator
是对求值器中各种地方的跟踪
that were passed when the evaluation happened.
在求值发生时会使用这些地方
And then here, here you see arrows.
在这里 你可以看到箭头
Arrow down means register saved.
下箭头代表寄存器的保存
So the first thing that happened is the environment got saved.
所以最先保存的是ENV寄存器
And over here, the environment got restored.
然后 在这里恢复ENV
so there are all the pairs of stack operations.
这些都是成对的栈操作
Now, if you go ahead and say
如果你更进一步
well, let's remember that we don't--that unev
我们记得
for instance, is a completely useless register.
UNEV是个完全没用的寄存器
And if we use the constant structure of the code
如果我们用固定结构的代码
well, we don't need, we don't need to save unev.
就不需要保存UNEV 因为完全用不上
And then, depending on how we set up the discipline of the--
然后 根据我们约定的
of calling other things that apply,
应用过程的准则
we may or may not need to save continue.
我们会选择是否保存CONTINUE
That's the first step I did.
这就是我们做的第一件事
And then we can look and see what's actually,
然后我们可以看看
what's actually needed.
实际需要些什么
See, we don't-- didn't really need to save env
其实在求值F的过程中
across-evaluating f
我们不需要保存ENV
because it wouldn't, it wouldn't trash it.
因为它不会被破坏
So if we take advantage of that
因此 如果我们利用这点
and see the evaluation of f here
这里对F的求值
doesn't really need to worry about,
完全不需要担心
about hurting env.
会破坏ENV
And similarly, the evaluation of x here
类似地 这里对X的求值
when the evaluator did that it said
当求值器进行求值时 它会说
Oh, I'd better preserve the function register around that
我最好保存好与之有关的FUN寄存器
because I might need it later.
因为后面也许会用得着
And I better preserve the argument list.
我最好也保存参数表
Whereas the compiler is now in a position to know
然而 在这如果是编译器的话
well, we didn't really need to save--
实际需要哪些寄存器
to do those saves and restores.
从而进行相关的保存与恢复
So in fact, all of the stack operations done by the evaluator
事实上 这里求值器做的所有栈操作
turned out to be unnecessary or overly pessimistic.
都证明是过于悲观而不必要
And the compiler is in a position to know that.
而编译器在这里是知道这一点的
Well that's the basic idea.
这是最基础的想法
We take the evaluator
我们把求值器
we eliminate the things that you don't need
剔除那些不需要的东西
that in some sense have nothing to do with the compiler at all
去除那些对于编译器完全无用的东西
just the evaluator
只保留求值的部分
and then you see which stack operations are unnecessary.
然后你可以看到哪些栈操作是不必要的
That's the basic structure of the compiler that's
这就是书中所描述的编译器
that's described in the book.
的基本结构
Let me just show you how a
我给你们展示一下这
that examples a little bit too simple.
这个简单的例子
To see how you, how you actually save a lot
为了说清楚 多余的东西是怎样保存的
let's look at a little bit more complicated expression.
我们来看一个稍复杂的表达式
(F (G X) 1)
And I'm not going to go through all the code.
我们不会讲解所有的代码
There's a, there's a fair pile of it.
因为代码有点多
I think there are, there are something like 16
我认为在求值器在处理它时
16 pairs of register saves and restores
大概会产生
as the evaluator walks through that.
16对保存-恢复操作
Here's a diagram of them.
这有一张图表
Let's see. You see what's going on.
演示了其中的过程
You start out by--
你从这里开始--
the evaluator says, oh, I'm about to do an application.
求值器说：“我要求值一个应用”
I'll preserve the environment. I'll restore it here.
在这里保存ENV 又在这里恢复
Then I'm about to do the first operand.
然后处理第一个运算对象
Here it recursively goes to the evaluator.
这是求值器的递归调用
The evaluator says, oh, this is an application,
求值器发现 这是一个应用
I'll save the environment
又会保存环境
do the operator of that combination, restore it here.
求值组合式的运算符 然后在这里恢复环境
This save--this restore matches that save.
这个恢复匹配的是这个保存操作
And so on.
以此类推
There's unev here,
这里的UNEV
which turns out to be completely unnecessary
完全没有必要存在
continues getting bumped around here.
CONTINUE寄存器不断地被保存-恢复
The function register is getting, getting saved
而FUN寄存器则是在
across the first operands, across the operands.
处理运算对象期间被保存
All sorts of things are going on.
这类的事情一直在发生
But if you say, well, what of those really were the business of
但如果你问 跟求值器相比
the compiler as opposed to the evaluator
编译器究竟要做什么？
you get rid of a whole bunch.
你会去掉一大堆东西
And then on top of that, if you say things like
在这个的基础上 如果你说
the evaluation of F doesn't hurt the environment register,
对F的求值不会修改ENV寄存器
or simply looking up the symbol X,
或者对符号X的查找
you don't have to protect the function register against that.
不需要特别保护FUN寄存器
So you come down to just a couple of, a couple of pairs here.
就得到了只有几对的保存-恢复操作
And still, you can do a little better.
然而 你还可以再优化一下
Look what's going on here with the environment register.
看看这里的ENV寄存器发生了什么
The environment register comes along and says, oh,
我们观察ENV寄存器的操作 发现
here's a combination.
这是一个组合式
This evaluator, by the way,
而这个求值器
doesn't know anything about G.
对G一无所知
So here it says, so it says,
所以在这 它说
I'd better save the environment register,
我最好保存ENV寄存器
because evaluating G might be
因为对G的求值
some arbitrary piece of code that would trash it
可能会修改ENV寄存器的值
and I'm going to need it later,
而我稍后可能会需要它
after this argument,
在这个参数之后
for doing the second argument.
在处理第二个参数的时候
So that's why this one didn't go away,
这就是为什么它没被优化掉
because the compiler made no assumptions about what G would do.
因为编译器没有对G将要做的事情做任何假设
On the other hand,
另一方面
if you look at what the second argument is,
如果你看看这里的第二个参数
that's just looking up one.
它只是查找“1”这个常量
That doesn't need this environment register.
这不需要ENV寄存器
So there's no reason to save it.
因此没必要保存它
So in fact, you can get rid of that one, too.
事实上 你也可以把这个也去掉
And from this whole pile of, of register operations,
这一堆寄存器操作
if you simply do a little bit of reasoning like that,
如果你像这样简单地推理的话
you get down to, I think, just two pairs of saves and restores.
只会剩下两对保存-恢复操作
And those, in fact, could go away further if you,
而这些 如果你知道关于G的某些信息的话
if you knew something about G.
可以进一步优化
So again, the general idea
基本的理念是
is that the reason the compiler can be better
编译器之所以更好
is that the interpreter doesn't know what it's about to encounter.
是因为解释器对于将要处理的东西一无所知
It has to be maximally pessimistic
它不得不以最悲观的方式保存东西
to protect itself.
来保护它自己
The compiler
而编译器
only has to deal with what actually had to be saved.
只需要保存实际需要的东西
And there are two reasons that something
某个东西是否需要保存
might not have to be saved.
有两种原因
One is that
一种是
what you're protecting it against,
你保护的东西
in fact, didn't trash the register,
不会修改寄存器
like it was just a variable look-up.
例如 变量查找
And the other one is,
另一种原因是
that the thing that you were saving it for
你所保存的东西
might turn out not to actually need it.
最后并不会被用到
So those are the two basic pieces of knowledge
因此 编译器正是利用了
that the compiler can take advantage of
这两条基本原则
in making the code more efficient.
来让代码变得更高效的
Let's break for questions.
有什么问题吗？
AUDIENCE: You kept saying that the uneval register,
学生: 你一直在说UNEV寄存器
unev register didn't need to be used at all.
UNEV寄存器完全不会被用到
Does that mean that you could just map a six-register machine?
是否意味着 机器只需要6个寄存器足矣？
Or is that, in this particular example,
或者是说 在这个特定的例子里
it didn't need to be used?
它没有被用到？
PROFESSOR: For the compiler,
教授: 对于编译器
you could generate code for the six-register, five, right?
你可以生成6个或5个寄存器的代码
Because that exp goes away also.
因为EXP寄存器也没有用到
Assuming--yeah, you can get rid of both exp and unev
是的 你可以把EXP和UNEV都去掉
because, see, those are data structures of the evaluator.
因为这些是求值器的数据结构
Those are all things that would be constants
以编译器的视角来看
from the point of view of the compiler.
这些东西都是常量
The only thing is
关键在于
this particular compiler is set up
这个特定编译器是被构造出来的
so that interpreted code and compiled code can coexist.
因此被解释的代码和被编译的代码可以共存
So the way to think about it is,
可以这样看待它
is maybe you build a chip
你构建了一个芯片
which is the evaluator,
它就是求值器
and what the compiler might do
而编译器可以做的就是
is generate code for that chip.
为这个芯片生成代码
It just wouldn't use two of the registers.
只是它不会用到两个寄存器而已
All right, let's take a break.
好 休息一会
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
[音乐]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
讲师： 哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
编译
We just looked at what the compiler is supposed to do.
我们刚才研究了编译器应该要做什么
Now let's very briefly look at how,
现在我们来简略地看看
how this gets accomplished.
这些目标如何达成
And I'm going to give no details.
而我不会给出细节
There's, there's a giant pile of code in the book
在书中有一大堆代码
that gives all the details.
展示了所有细节
But what I want to do is just show you the,
我要做的 是给你们展示
the essential idea here.
其中的关键思想
Worry about the details some other time.
换个时间再来关心细节
Let's imagine that we're compiling an expression
设想我们正在编译一条表达式
that looks like there's some operator
这里有一些运算符
and there are two arguments.
和两个参数
Now, the--
现在
what's the code that the compiler should generate?
这个编译器会生成什么代码?
Well, first of all,
首先
it should recursively go off
它会递归运行
and compile the operator.
编译运算符
So it says, I'll compile the operator.
它说 我要编译运算符
And where I'm going to need that
最后我需要让它们的结果
is to be in the function register, eventually.
存放在FUN寄存器中
So I'll compile some instructions
所以我编译一些指令
that will compile the operator
它们会编译运算符
and end up with the result in the function register.
最后把结果放在FUN寄存器中
The next thing it's going to do,
接下来我要做的是
another piece is to say,
另一个代码片段则说
I have to compile the first argument.
我要编译第一个参数
So it calls itself recursively.
因此它递归调地用自己
And let's say the result will go into val.
而结果会被放在VAL中
And then what it's going to need to do is
接下来需要做的是
start setting up the argument list.
建立起参数表
So it'll say, assign to argl cons of fetch--
(ASSIGN ARGL (CONS (FETCH --
so it generates this literal instruction--
它会生成这些代码
fetch of val onto empty list.
(FETCH VAL) '()))
However,
然而
it might have to work--  when it gets here,
当它到这里时
it's going to need the environment.
它可能需要环境
It's going to need whatever environment was here
它需要环境
in order to do this evaluation of the first argument.
这是求值第一个参数所需要的
So it has to ensure that
因此 它需要保证
the compilation of this operand,
对运算对象的编译
or it has to protect the function register
或者说它需要保护FUN寄存器
against whatever might happen in the compilation of this operand.
来应对编译运算对象时发生的各种情况
So it puts a note here and says, oh,
因此它在这做了个标注说
this piece should be done preserving the environment register.
这个片段需要保护ENV寄存器
Similarly, here,
与之类似 这里
after it gets done compiling the first operand,
在完成第一个运算对象的编译后
it's going to say, I'd better--
它会说 我最好--
I'm going to need to know the environment for the second operand.
我需要知道第二个运算对象的环境
So it puts a little note here, saying,
所以它在这做了个标注
yeah, this is also done preserving env.
这里也需要保护ENV
Now it goes on and says, well,
现在它继续运行
the next chunk of code
下一段代码
is the one that's going to compile the second argument.
是要编译第二个参数
And let's say
它将会
And let's say it'll compile it with a targeted to val, as they say.
把编译的结果按约定放入到VAL中
And then it'll generate the literal instruction,
随后它会生成一条指令
building up the argument list.
从而建立起参数表
So it'll say, assign to argl
(ASSIGN ARGL
cons of the new value it just got onto the old argument list.
(CONS (FETCH VAL) (FETCH ARGL))
However,
然而
in order to have the old argument list,
为了取得旧的参数表
it better have arranged that the argument list didn't get trashed
它最好保证这期间发生的任何事情
by whatever happened in here.
都不影响旧的参数表
So it puts a little note here and says,
因此它在这做了个标注说
oh, this has to be done preserving argl.
哦 这里需要保护ARGL
Now it's got the argument list set up.
现在参数表就建立好了
And it's all ready to go to apply dispatch.
现在可以准备去APPLY-DISPATCH了
It generates this literal instruction.
它生成了这条指令
Because now it's got the arguments in argl
因为现在参数都在ARGL中
and the operator in fun,
运算符在FUN中
but wait, it's only got the operator in fun
如果只是单纯地把运算符放到FUN寄存器中
if it had ensured that this block of code
就需要它保证这块代码
didn't trash what was in the function register.
不会破坏FUN寄存器里的东西
So it puts a little note here and says,
所以它在这做了个标注说
oh, yes, all this stuff here
这里的所有东西
had better be done preserving the function register.
最好能够在保护FUN寄存器的情况下完成
So that's the little--so when it starts ticking--
所以这就是--
so basically, what the
基本上来说
what the compiler does is
编译器所做的就是
append a whole bunch of code sequences.
追加一大堆的代码
See, what it's got in it is little primitive pieces of things
而这些代码之中都是一些基本运算
like how to look up a symbol,
比如符号查找
how to do a conditional.
条件分支的处理
Those are all little pieces of things.
都是一些琐碎的事情
And then it appends them together in this sort of discipline.
然后按照这种准则将它们追加到一起
So the basic means of combining things
因此 组合的基本手段就是
is to append two code sequences.
将一段代码追加到另一段的后面
That's what's going on here.
就是这里发生的事情
And it's a little bit tricky.
这有点取巧
The idea is that it appends two code sequences,
向一段代码后面追加代码的思路是
taking care to preserve a register.
小心保护寄存器
So the actual append operation looks like this.
追加操作看起来像这样
What it wants to do is say, if--
它要做的是
here's what it means to append two code sequences.
代码的追加是这么来做的
So if sequence one needs register--
如果SEQ1需要寄存器--
I should change this.
我应该改一下这个
Append sequence one to sequence two,
在SEQ1后面追加SEQ2
preserving some register.
并保护一些寄存器
Let me say, and.
这里改成AND
So it's clear that sequence one comes first.
这样的话前后顺序就清楚了
So if sequence two needs the register
如果SEQ2需要寄存器
and sequence one modifies the register,
而SEQ1又修改了寄存器
then the instructions that the compiler spits out,
那么编译器生成的指令是
are save the register.
保存寄存器
Here's the code.
这就是代码
You generate this code.
生成这段代码
Save the register,
保存寄存器
and then you put out the recursively compiled stuff for sequence one.
然后写下递归编译SEQ1的结果
And then you restore the register.
然后恢复寄存器
And then you put out the recursively compiled stuff
再写下递归编译
for sequence two.
SEQ2的结果
That's in the case where you need to do it.
这就是你需要做的
Sequence two actually needs the register,
实际上SEQ2需要寄存器
and sequence one actually clobbers it.
而SEQ1改动了它
So that's sort of if. Otherwise,
否则的话
all you spit out is sequence one followed by sequence two.
得到的就是SEQ1后面跟着SEQ2
So that's the basic operation
这就是把两个代码片段
for sticking together these bits of code fragments,
连接到一起的基本操作
these bits of instructions into a sequence.
把这些指令组合成序列
And you see, from this point of view,
我们可以发现 从这个角度看
the difference between the interpreter and the compiler, in some sense,
解释器和编译器的区别
is that where the compiler has these preserving notes,
是编译器有保护寄存器的标注
and says, maybe I'll actually generate the
上面记录着
saves and restores and maybe I won't,
是否需要生成保存-恢复代码
the interpreter being maximally pessimistic
而解释器会以最悲观的方式处理
always has a save and restore here.
总是会进行保存-恢复
That's the essential difference.
这就是关键的区别
Well, in order to do this, of course,
为了实现这个
the compiler needs some theory of
编译器需要一些理论
what code sequences need and modifier registers.
来确定代码序列会需要、又会修改哪些寄存器
So the tiny little fragments that you put in, like
所以你放入的小片段
the basic primitive code fragments,
例如这段基础代码
say, what are the operations that you do
当你查找一个变量时
when you look up a variable?
进行了哪些操作？
What are the sequence of things that you do
你又是做了些什么
when you compile a constant
来编译一个常量
or apply a function?
或者应用一个函数
Those have little notations in there
它们都会带有一些标注
about what they need and what they modify.
说明了它们需要的和修改的寄存器
So the bottom-level data structures--
所以底层的数据结构
Well, I'll say this.
我会这样讲
A code sequence to the compiler looks like this.
传递给编译器的代码序列大概是这样
It has the actual sequence of instructions.
它里面有实际的指令序列
And then, along with it,
跟它一起的还有
there's the set of registers modified.
一组被修改的寄存器
And then there's the set of registers needed.
还有一组需要的寄存器
So that's the information the compiler has
为了能够执行此操作
that it draws on in order to be able to do this operation.
编译器必须要掌握这些信息
And where do those come from? Well.
它们从哪来呢
Well, those come from, you might expect,
它们来自于--你们可能也想到了
for the very primitive ones,
对于那些最基本的片段
we're going to put them in by hand.
我们会手工添加
And then, when we combine two sequences,
然后 当我们组合两个序列时
we'll figure out what these things should be.
我们会计算出这两个集合
So for example, a very primitive one, let's see.
举一个非常基本的例子
How about doing a register assignment.
例如做一个寄存器赋值
So a primitive sequence might say,
因此 基本代码片段会说
oh, it's code fragment.
噢 它是个代码片段
Its code instruction is assigned to R1, fetch of R2.
代码的指令部分是(ASSIGN R1 (FETCH R2))
So this is an example.
这个例子就是这样的
That might be an example of a sequence of instructions.
一段指令序列大概就是这样
And along with that, it'll say, Oh
和它在一起的是
oh, what I need to remember is that that modifies R1
它需要记得修改了R1
and then it needs R2.
然后它需要R2
So when you're first building this compiler,
因此当你开始构建编译器时
you put in little fragments of stuff like that.
你放入这样的一个片段
And now, when it combines two sequences,
当它组合两个序列时
if I'm going to combine,
我要组合
let's say, sequence one,
代码片段S1
that modifies a bunch of registers M1,
修改了一组寄存器M1
and needs a bunch of registers N1.
并且需要一组寄存器N1
And I'm going to combine that with sequence two.
并且我要把它和序列S2组合到一起
That modifies a bunch of registers M2,
后者修改了一组寄存器M2
and needs a bunch of registers N2.
并且需要一组寄存器N2
Then, well, we can reason it out.
这样我们就能得出结果
The new code fragment,
新的代码片段是这样的
sequence one, and-- followed by sequence two,
指令序列S1后面跟着S2
well, what's it going to modify?
它要修改什么?
The things that it will modify are the things
它要修改的是
that are modified either by sequence one or sequence two.
被S1或者被S2修改的寄存器
So the union of these two
N1和N2的并集
sets are what the new thing modifies.
就是新的修改集
And then you say, well, what is this--
然后你问
what registers is it going to need?
又需要哪些寄存器？
It's going to need the things that are,
需要这些寄存器的是
first of all, needed by sequence one.
首先 一定是序列S1需要的
So what it needs is sequence one.
因此必然有N1
And then, well, not quite all of the ones
然后 并不是N2里面的所有元素
that are needed by sequence two.
我们都需要
What it needs are the ones that are needed by sequence two
新的修改集需要N2中那些
that have not been set up by sequence one.
没有被S1修改过的寄存器
So it's sort of the union of
所以 这个并集是N1并上
the things that sequence two needs
序列S2的需要集N2
minus the ones that sequence one modifies.
减去序列S1的修改集M1
Because it worries about setting them up.
因为它关心的是如何设置它们
So there's the basic structure of the compiler.
这就是编译器的基本结构
The way you do register optimizations is you
我们进行寄存器优化的方式是
you have some strategies for what needs to be preserved.
一些策略来应对需要保护的东西
That depends on a data structure.
这取决于数据结构
Well, it depends on the operation of what it means to put things together.
这取决于将东西组合在一起的操作
Preserving something, that depends on knowing
想知道要保护哪些东西
what registers are needed and modified by these code fragments.
就需要知道这段代码需要以及修改的寄存器
That depends on having little data structures,
这就需要我们有一个数据结构
which say, a code sequence is the actual instructions,
它不但要存放实际的指令序列
what they modify and what they need.
它修改了什么 又需要什么
That comes from, at the primitive level, building it in.
这些信息来自于--最基本的情况是内置的
At the primitive level,
对于最基本的情况
it's going to be completely obvious
我们可以容易地知道
what something needs and modifies.
需要哪些寄存器 又修改了哪些
Plus,
另外
this particular way that says, when I build up bigger ones,
利用这个特定的方法构建复杂指令时
here's how I generate the new set of registers modified
我们可以像这样生成新的修改集
and the new set of registers needed.
以及新的需要集
And that's the whole-- well, I shouldn't say that's the whole thing.
这就是全部的内容 -- 我不该这么说
That's the whole thing except for about
这就是书里面大概30页的细节
about 30 pages of details in the book.
的核心内容了
But it is a perfectly usable rudimentary compiler.
但它是一个完全可用的初级编译器
Let me kind of show you what it does.
让我给你展示一下它能做什么
Suppose we start out with recursive factorial.
假设我们从一个递归阶乘开始
And these slides are going to be much too small to read.
这些幻灯片的字太小不适合阅读
I just want to flash through the code
我只想快速翻一下代码
and show you about how much it is.
让你们看看它有多少代码
That starts out with--
代码从这开始--
here's a first block of it,
这是代码的第一部分
where it compiles a procedure entry
这里编译了一个过程入口
and does a bunch of assignments.
并进行了一些赋值操作
And this thing is basically up through the part where
这基本上对应了解释器中
sets up to do the predicate
进行判断之前的部分
and test whether the predicate's true.
并判断谓词是否成立
The second part
第二部分是
is what results from-- in the recursive call to fact of n minus one.
递归调用N-1的阶乘的结果
And this last part
最后一部分是
is coming back from that
从那里返回
and then taking care of the constant case.
并处理递归的基本情况
So that's about how much code it would produce for factorial.
这就是编译阶乘会生成的代码量
We could make this compiler much, much better, of course.
当然 我们可以把这个编译器做得更好
The main way we could make it better is
优化它的主要方式是
to allow the compiler to make any assumptions at all
当你调用一个过程时
about what happens when you call a procedure.
允许编译器做任何假设
So this compiler, for instance,
举例来说
doesn't even know, say, that multiplication
这个编译器甚至不知道
you say, is something that could be coded in line.
乘法可以被内联执行
Instead, it sets up this whole mechanism.
它则会自行构建起整个机制
It goes to apply-dispatch.
进行APPLY-DISPATCH
That's a tremendous waste,
这是极大的浪费
because what you do every time you go to apply-dispatch
因为 每当你进行APPLY-DISPATCH时
is you have to concern about this argument list,
你都要关心这个参数表
because it's a very general thing you're going to.
因为它是个很普遍的操作
In any real compiler, of course,
在任何真实的编译器中
you're going to have registers for holding arguments.
你会有寄存器来暂存参数
And you're going to start preserving
你要开始保护
saving the way you use those registers
保存这些寄存器
similar to the same strategy here.
和这里的策略相近
So that's probably the very main way
因此 我们可能主要通过这个方法
this particular compiler in the book could be fixed.
来优化书中这个特定的编译器
There are other things like
还有其它的一些方法
looking up variable values and
比如查找变量的值
making more efficient primitive operations,
使用更高效的基本操作
and all sorts of things.
等等方法
Essentially, a good Lisp compiler
本质上来说 一个好的Lisp编译器
can absorb an arbitrary amount of effort.
可以吸收任意数量的努力
And probably one of the reasons
可能这其中的一个原因是
Lisp is slow
跟FORTRAN这类语言相比
with compared to languages like FORTRAN
Lisp就要慢一些
is that, if you look over history
如果你回头审视历史
the amount of effort that's gone into building Lisp compilers,
会发现人们为构建Lisp编译器而呕心沥血
it's nowhere near the amount of effort
但也远远没有接近
that's gone into FORTRAN compilers.
构建FORTRAN编译器的工作量
And maybe that's something that will
在接下来的几年
that will change over the next couple of years.
情况可能会发生变化
OK, let's break.
好吧 就讲到这里
Questions?
有问题吗
AUDIENCE: One of the very first classes--
学生: 很早的一个课时里--
I don't know if it was during class or after class-
我不记得是课上还是课后--
you showed me the, the
你向我们展示了
say, addition has a primitive that we don't see,
ADD操作有一些我们看不到的基本运算
and-percent add or something like that.
类似于ADD%之类的
Is that because,
这是因为
if you're doing inline code
你想把代码内联为
you'd want to just do it for two operators, operands?
专门针对二元运算对象的运算么？
But if you had more operands,
但如果你有更多的运算对象
you'd want to do something special?
你会做什么特殊的事情吗？
PROFESSOR: Yeah, you're looking in the actual scheme implementation.
教授: 你看的是Scheme的实际实现
There's a plus, and a plus is some operator.
其中有一个‘+’ 这是一个运算符
And then if you go look inside the code for plus,
如果你看‘+’的源代码
you see something called--
你会看到一些叫做--
I forget-- and-percent plus or something like that.
我记不清了--可能叫ADD%、PLUS之类的东西
And what's going on there is
这里所进行的
is that particular kind of optimization.
就是你说的那种优化
Because, see, general plus takes an arbitrary number of arguments.
因为 广义的‘+’接受任意数量的参数
So the most general plus
所以 广义加法
says, oh, if I have an argument list,
会说：如果我有一个参数表
I'd better cons it up in some list
我最好将它们用CONS连接到表里
and then figure out how many there were or something like that.
并指出有多少个参数
That's terribly inefficient,
这样效率非常低下
especially since most of the time you're probably adding two numbers.
因为大部分时间你在把两个数相加
You don't want to really have to cons this argument list.
你不必把整个参数表连接到一起
So what you'd like to do is build
所以你想做的是
the code for plus with a bunch of entries.
构建把一堆东西相加的代码
So most of what it's doing is the same.
所以它做的大部分事情是一样的
However, there might be a special entry
但这里可能有个特殊的入口
that you'd go to if you knew there were only two arguments.
如果你知道只有两个参数
And those you'll put in registers.
你会把它们放到寄存器中
they won't be in an argument list
它们不需要参数表
and you won't have to CONS.
你也不必用CONS连接它们
That's how a lot of these things work.
这就是这些东西工作的原理
OK, let's take a break.
好吧 下课吧
MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
本项目主页
https://github.com/DeathKing/Learning-SICP